Inventory of the Japanese diaspora collection 2017C46.12104235
Hoover Institution Archives
Japanese diaspora collection
1889-1944
Hoover Institution Archives
2017C46.12104235
6.3 linear feet 2 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 2 oversize folders, 528 digital files (.53 GB)
Reports, pamphlets, postcards, other printed matter, photographs, and digital materials relating to Japanese immigration to the United States and elsewhere, the Japanese community in the United States, and Japanese American internment during World War II.
Digital files
Box 1-6
Shelf 134.02
Map case
Drawer H6
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual or digital material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at https://searchworks.stanford.edu. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Japanese diaspora collection consists of reports, rare historical documents, digital files, rosters, photographs, maps, pamphlets, posters, postcards, and other printed matter relating to the Japanese diaspora, primarily to the Americas. The collection includes series such as the Japantowns of San Francisco and Los Angeles, the departing ports of Yokohama and Kobe in Japan, Japanese export industry and shipping companies, internment camps during World War II, Japanese agriculture and flower growing businesses in the United States, and Japanese government survey reports on the Japanese settlement in Brazil, among others.
Japan--Emigration and immigration.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; Japanese--United States.
- Kobe
  - Postcards of the Kobe port, Meiji-Taisho (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Nine postcards of the Kobe port, of which four were written and mailed (Kansas, Santa Barbara CA, Shimonokeki, Yamaguchi, and Kagawa).
  - Postcard of Motomachi, Kobe, Showa 13? (1938) (Box 1)
    One postcard (photograph) of flooded Motomachi, Kobe.
- Los Angeles
  - 加州羅府日本人商業区域明細図 (Kashū Rafū Nihonjin shōgyō meisaizu), 近藤謙二 (Kondō, Kenji), Los Angeles, 1926 (Map case)
    "Detailed Plan of Japanese Commercial District in Los Angeles, California." A detailed map of Japanese businesses, with a list of establishments by type, location, and name. Advertisements by some of these businesses are on the back.
  - 御帰朝之栞 附羅府名所案内 (Gokichō no shiori: fu Rafū meisho an’nai), Rafu Eagle Hotel (Rafū Īguru hoteru), Los Angeles, 1925 (Box 1)
    "Leaflet for Returning to Japan: Including Los Angeles Guidebook." Detailed information about immigration, marriage, and tariffs on imported items in Japan. There are many Japanese business advertisements, which sell gift items to Japanese returning to Japan, cruise ship companies, and hotels.
- San Francisco
  - 桑港航路案内 (Sanfuranshisuko kōro annai), 日本郵船会社 (Nihon Yūsen Kabushiki Gaisha) (Box 1)
    Guide to Sea Voyage to San Francisco. Detailed travel advice from Japan to the United States: explains the U.S. immigration laws and includes a detailed list of sea fares from various ports in Japan and China to Hawaii and San Francisco.
  - 桑港案内 (Sanfuranshisuko annai), 長尾 峰三郎 (Nagao, Minesaburō), 桑港日本人旅舘組合 (Sanfuranshisuko), San Francisco, 1931 (Box 1)
    Guide of San Francisco. Details about Japanese-related businesses in San Francisco.
  - San Francisco: Photographs in Black, A. Wittemann, The Albertype Co., New York, 1889 (Box 1)
    Photographs include Chinatown, Chinese class, and a farm in California. Likely to have been brought back as a souvenir to Japan from San Francisco.
  - 桑港仏教会開教三十年記念誌 (Sōkō bukkyōkai kaikyō sanjūnen kinenshi), 桑港仏教会 文書部 (Sōkō bukkyōkai bunshobu), 陰山鐵二郎 (Kageyama, Tetsujirō), San Francisco, 1930 (Map case)
    Thirtieth Anniversary of Buddhist Church in San Francisco. Detailed history of Japanese Buddhist church (Honpa Honganji) of San Francisco, the oldest Japanese Buddhist church in the continental United States. Some information about Japanese-language schools. Includes many photographs of the church members and activities, as well as a list of kakochō (deceased members by place of origin, kaimyō, and the year of death).
  - 明治期米国桑港(サンフランシスコ)地震震災邦人義金募集 (Meijiki Beikoku Sōkō (San Francisco) jishin shinsai hōjin gikin boshū), circa 1906 (Box 1)
    Fund Raising for the Earthquake Disaster Relief of the Japanese in San Francisco in the Meiji Era. "San Francisco has suffered from an unprecedented natural disaster. We have heard that our imperial court has gifted relief fund and we sincerely feel the benevolence of the emperor. We feel compassionate for our countrymen who have suffered from this natural disaster, thousands of miles away from home. We have collected disaster relief funds and telegraphed the Imperial Japanese counsel general in San Francisco." A list of founders of the Association of San Francisco Natural Disaster Relief: trade companies from Kobe, Osaka, Kyoto, Yokkaichi, Nagoya, Shizuoka, Yokohama, and Tokyo
  - 於桑港ペンシルバニア号 大日本帝国艦隊歓迎プログラム (Itaru Sōkō Penshirubania gō Dainihon teikoku kantai kangei puroguramu), 1926 August 2 (Box 1)
    "Welcoming the Japanese Imperial Navy, the Pennsylvania, San Francisco." The program includes various events and finishes with the United States national anthem.
- Yokohama
  - "Sample Exhibition of Exports in Japan Is Displayed at the Yokohama Commercial and Industrial Museum under Management of the Yokohama Chamber of Commerce and Industry,", circa 1929 (Box 1)
    The Yokohama Commercial and Industrial Museum was opened in 1929 as part of the Yokohama restoration projects after the Great Kanto Earthquake. It played a pivotal role in commercial development of Yokohama, where the largest port in Japan is located.
  - 昭和三年於横浜港内 御大礼特別大観艦式 (Shōwa 3nen oite Yokohama kōnai gotairei tokubetsu taikan kanshik), undated (Box 1)
    "Navy Ship Parade Inspected by the Emperor at Yokohama Port in 1928." Postcards depicting the Japanese imperial navy parade at Yokohama port.
- Agricultural and Flower Growing Businesses
  - One black and white photo of agricultural activities by Japanese American farmers, 1941 February 1 (Box 3)
  - Photo album of California Chrysanthemum Growers Association and their families (Box 3)
- Export Industry
  - 帝国製麻株式会社 八 亞麻碎莖 (Teikoku seima kabushiki kaisha amasa saikei), Meiji-Taisho (Box 1)
    "Linen Breaker at the Teikoku Linen Co." Four postcards showing different export industries in Japan during the Meiji and Taisho eras.
  - 足尾銅山通銅選鉱場内部 (Ashio dōzan tsūdō senkōjō naibu), Meiji-Taisho (Box 1)
    Inner view of the Tsudo dressing plants, Ashio copper mines.
  - 二本松輸出羽二重株式会社織物工場 (Nihonmatsu yushutsu Habutae kabushiki kaisha orimono kōjō), Meiji-Taisho (Box 1)
    The weaving department of Nihonmatsu exportation Habutae Co. Ltd.
  - 若林製糸紡績株式会社浪江工場 工場全景/繰糸場の一部 (Wakabayashi seishi bōseki kabushiki kaisha Namie kōjō), Meiji-Taisho (Box 1)
    Namie factory of the Wakabayashi Silk Mill Textile Co. Ltd.
- Family and Other
  - Two black and white photos, 1940 (Box 2)
- Hokkaido Immigration
  - 北海道移住民汽車賃汽船賃割引券 (Hokkaidō ijū jūmin kishachin kisenchin waribiki ken) (Box 1)
    Discount coupon for trains and ships for immigrants to Hokkaido, used by a Japanese immigrant to Hokkaido in ?.
  - 第五 北海道移住案内 (Daigo Hokkaidō ijū an’nai), Editor:北海道拓殖部 (Hokkaidō Takushokubu), Sapporo, 1897 (Box 1)
    Guide for Immigration to Hokkaido, Vol. 5.
  - 北海道移住案内 第二十八 (Hokkaidō ijū an’nai dai nijū nachi), Editor:北海道拓殖部 (Hokkaidō Takushokubu), Sapporo, 1929 (Box 1)
    Guide for Immigration to Hokkaido, Vol. 28.
  - 北海道移住案内 第二十九 (Hokkaidō ijū an’nai dai nijūkyū), Editor:北海道拓殖部 (Hokkaidō Takushokubu), Sapporo, 1931 (Box 1)
    Guide for Immigration to Hokkaido, Vol. 29.
  - 北海道移住案内 第三十一 (Hokkaidō ijū an’nai dai sanjūichi), Editor:北海道拓殖部 (Hokkaidō Takushokubu), Sapporo, 1933 (Box 1)
    Guide for Immigration to Hokkaido, Vol. 31.
- Internment Camps
  - Nine black and white photos (Box 2)
  - ゼローム共同企業組合 記念号 (Zerōmu kyōdōn kigyō kumiai Kinen gō), 1944 April 15 (Box 2)
    Jerome Cooperative Commemorative Issue. Records of the cooperative at Jerome relocation center, Arkansas, and directory of the incarcerated at the center by name, birth place, age, address in the United States, profession before the relocation, and current profession. The directory is organized by block at the camp. Directory of the cooperative members and their roles. Journal of major events at Jerome.
  - Poston War Relocation Center Directory (Box 2, Digital files)
    Poston camp II directory scanned images; Poston census as of March 31, 1944 done at each camp by a government directive. The copy was digitized by Robert Iwamasa from a hard copy given to Mas Hashimoto. P-final accountability roster. Data extracted by Tak Kohatsu from FAR records. Two sets of data, one by name and the second by camp-block-unit.
    Digital files consist of censuses, include basic identifying information about internees, taken at the Poston Internment Camp. Two of the censuses are handwritten in Kanji.
- Japanese Images
  - Group of Japanese boys and girls (Box 1)
    One postcard in Japan during the Meiji era depicting children in the countryside. Addressed from Hornshawn (in Japan?) to Mrs. Betteridge, Surrey, United Kingdom.
- Private Sector Exchanges
  - Photo albums of Mainichi News reporter, S. Onogi
    Photo albums (5 volumes) of Mainichi Newspaper reporter and his trips to Los Angeles, Vladivostok, and China in the 1920s and 1930s. Onogi joined the Mainichi Newspaper in 1920 and travelled to Los Angeles as a member of the Kwansei Gakuin University (based in Nishinomiya, Japan) junior high school baseball team in 1928. Includes one photo with the Japanese actor Kamiyama Sojin, who appeared in Hollywood movies in the 1920s.
    - Trip to Vladivostok (Box 5)
    - Trip to California, including Kawansei Gakuin University baseball tour in 1928 (Box 2)
    - Japan (Box 2)
    - Family photos (Box 6)
    - Japan (Box 5)
  - Photo albums of Japanese women attending the Chicago World Fair, 1933
    Photo albums (2 volumes) of Japanese women attendants to the Chicago World Fair (1933) from their trip on board a ship to the United States and their activities at the Japanese pavilion.
    - General fair pictures (Box 2)
    - Photos of companion activities at the Chicago World Fair (Box 6)
  - Photo albums of a Japanese General Electric employee's trip to the United States, 1937-1938 (Box 4)
    Photo albums of a Japanese General Electric employee's training trip to Hawaii, San Francisco, and New York. Includes photographs of the first class passengers on the Taiyo Maru from Yokohama to San Francisco, the port of San Francisco, and Stanford University.
  - Printed photo album of a Japanese business mission to the United States, 1911 (Box 6)
    A printed photo album (1 volume) of a Japanese business mission to the United States in 1911, led by Baron Eiichi (Yeiichi) Shibusawa, with a list of mission members.
- Shipping Companies
  - 増訂 渡米之栞 (Zōtei tobei no shiori), 一柳松庵 (Ichiyanagi, Shō’an), 佐々木勘助 (Sasaki, Kansuke), Tokyo, 1902 (Box 1)
    Guide for Moving to America: Expanded Edition. Detailed information about how to move to America and find a job. The cover has an advertisement by Toyo Kisen Kaisha. Includes a map of Seattle in Japanese.
  - 旅行安全三徳汽車時間表 (Ryokō anzen santoku kisha jikanhyō), 旅行安全合資会社 (Ryokō anzen gōshi kaisha), Tokyo, 1901 (Box 1)
    "Ryoko anzen santoku kisha Time Table." Timetable and fares of train and cruise in Japan and cruise to Europe and the United States. Includes a telegraph request form. The front page is an advertisement by Mitsui Gofukuya, which developed into Mitsui & Co., which worked as an immigration agency later.
  - N.Y.K. Orient-California, January 1933 - February 1934, circa 1934 (Box 1)
    Assorted cruise line brochures and schedule brought back to Japan.
- World War II
  - 簡易保険で銃後を護れ 保険金五十億園突破 (Kani hoken de jūgo o Mamore. Hoken kin gojū okuen toppa) (Box 1)
    "Protect the Country behind the Front Line with the State Life Insurance." "Have Reached Five Billion Yen in State Life Insurance Premiums." Two propaganda postcards in Japan during the Meiji and pre-WWII eras.
  - 赤十字社病院船博愛丸/戦地救護事業の状況 (Sekijūjisha byō’insen Hakuai Maru: Senchi kyūgo jigyō no jōkyō) (Box 1)
    Red Cross hospital ship Hakuai Maru: relief effort in the war zones.
- Hawaii
  - Hawai zairy ū Niigata kenjin ryakureki shashinch ō, photograph album, 1921 (Digital files, Box 2)
  - Hawai Nihonjin hatten meikan: B ōchō ban, photograph album, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Digital files)